[Music]
Hi, good morning. How are you? Hey, how
are you? Um, thanks for thanks for
jumping on and thanks for your your
patience on this. Um, yeah, as I said,
really excited to kick this off. So,
I'll just uh leave uh the presentation
to you. Over to you guys. All right.
Thank you very much. Hi, everybody.
Welcome. Uh my name is Josh Long. I work
on the Spring team and uh I am here to
talk to you all about the amazing Spring
AI project which by the buy uh releases
a GA release on uh 20 May. So that's
just uh what is that you know seven
short days away. And uh and indeed I
think there's even a a final sort of
release candidate uh or maybe it's a
final I don't know it's a release
candidate today or sometime very soon.
So be on the lookout for that. And uh
the whole purpose of Spring AI is to
sort of commoditize a lot of the
patterns that people realize that they
need when working with uh AI engineering
patterns. I think we in the Java and
Spring communities are uniquely well
situated to take uh advantage of this
moment in time uh to uh to to sort of
integrate uh AI into our applications.
And when we do that, we find that as
amazing as AI technologies are today,
they're not perfect and there are some
drawbacks. And so we see certain uh
problems and and well understood
patterns. For example, it's hard to get
an AI model to stay focused on one
particular outcome. So you give it a
system prompt. Uh they're stateless.
That is to say, they forget every single
uh you know, they forget what you've
said after every single request. So you
you're you're meant to uh provide a
transcript. That's called chat memory.
Uh they don't know how to ex to
integrate with the external world. So
you give them tool calling. They don't
know about your data. you prompt stuff
which is to say you take data and put it
in the body of the text sent to the AM
model. Uh but what data? That's the
question. Not all models can support all
your data. Certainly it's it's variable
and it depends on the model and the size
of your data. But there is for all of
them a finite sort of upper bound. Some
much larger than others, but still. So
in order to limit how much data you send
just to be sensible and to avoid the
complexity and dollars and cents cost,
use things like rag retrieval augmented
generation and vector stores which make
it easy to uh do sim semantic similarity
searches for data. And of course,
finally, these chat models are just
that. their chat models. They like to
chat and they sometimes do so
confidently even when they're dead
wrong. So you have to make sure that you
evaluate their output. So today we're
going to look at how you can use Spring
AI to uh sort of meet the uh moment with
um uh with some of these kind of use
cases in hand. So what I'm going to do
is I'm going to build a little dog
adoption shelter uh thing, right? We're
going to build a shelter for dogs that
you can adopt. And we're going to do so
in terms of, you know, thinking about
this dog that I learned about during the
pandemic whose owner went viral. the uh
the owner, this woman, she put was
trying to put up this dog for adoption,
and she described this dog very
hysterically. She says, "There's not a
very big market for neurotic,
man-hating, animal-hating,
children-hating dogs that look like
gremlins." And I think about this this
ad a lot. I mean, don't get me wrong,
very, very hysterically funny ad. And
the dog is super cute looking. And so,
this ad went viral. I mean, here it is
in uh People magazine. Here is the dog
in
Buzzfeed. and uh you know you know the
viral Chihuahua the demonic Chihuahua
and then of course here's the dog in the
New York Times as one does right so I
think about this dog a lot right like
what let's build a little service to
sort of make it easy for somebody to
adopt the dog of their dreams or uh you
know in this case nightmare so we're
going to go here to startso your
one-stop shop for generating new
applications and uh we're going to stick
to uh snapshots today obviously Wi-Fi
permitting oh goodness of all the times
for this to go slow oh my goodness oh
There we go. Okay, don't fret. I won't I
won't either. Okay, so what we're going
to do is we're going to build an
assistant. I'm going to call it as such.
I'll bring in uh the open AI support,
bring in the web support, bring in
Spring Data JDBC. Now, mind you, I've
already got a Postgres instance with the
vector store capability built in. So,
I'll use PG Vector. I've already got
that running. I'll bring in the Gravium
native image support. And uh I think
maybe I'll get the actuator as well. And
uh that looks like it's fine to me. You
can use any of a dozen different models.
I mean, OpenAI, Bedrock, Gemini, Alama,
whatever. You can use any any of I mean,
there's a bazillion different vector
databases. All the big ones that you can
imagine are all there as well. So, we're
going to open that up. Oh, you know what
else I want to do? Last thing. I also
want uh to build an MCP client. Okay.
So, go to the downloads directory here.
Going to delete the existing one that I
erently uh created. Just a second
though. Hit enter. That'll give me a zip
file. What is this? Okay. Go back to
that. go over here and we're going to go
back to my zip file here, ls, okay, uo
assistant.zip and uh that'll open up and
what we're going to do is we're going to
build an application that talks to a
database. Okay. Uh I'm going to bring in
some dependencies here as well. Before
we do that, so we're going to bring in a
uh a dependency for Spring AI Advisor
Vector Store, which is a custom one that
we're going to need. I'm going to switch
us to snapshots. Okay, so we'll go over
here. Uh okay, very good. snapshot and
uh you know the question is will it
recognize what dependencies I want looks
like it looks like it yep that's a
snapshot very good so let's go ahead and
build the application yeah first things
first this application is going to talk
to a SQL database so we'll specify as
much here we'll say spring data source
JDBC URL is a JDBC PostgresQL localhost
my database you should obviously
externalize these as environment
variables you wouldn't put them in your
your credentials like that but I am
doing the wrong thing do as I today and
as I as I do there's that. Uh we also
are going to want to in initialize a
vector store. So I'll tell it to
initialize a schema should that become
necessary. Uh and uh okay I think we're
ready to go. Let's build a controller.
And this is going to be an assistant
controller that'll help people answer
questions about the dogs uh in the
shelter. So we'll have an uh you know uh
assistant endpoint here string inquire
and we we'll accept a question from the
user to interview basically the shelter
about the dogs in the shelter right and
uh we're going to have an AI model
that'll do that work for us to answer
those questions for us to help people
get the dog of their of their dreams or
uh indeed nightmare. So so we're going
to go ahead and do that. And uh what
model are we using? Well like I said
when we initialize the program we're
using open AI but there's many you can
use. Make sure that you've specified a
credential like that. Right? I've
already done that as environment
variables offscreen, but just trust me
that it's been done and forgive me for
not leaking my API credential. So, first
things first, let's try this out. Huh?
So, this.ai dot um dot uh
uh what is that? Prompt user. And the
user prompt is the question being sent
from the user. Uh, we're going to call
the model, get the content back as a
string, although you can get it
structured as a strongly typed object as
well using entity, right? There's a
another variant there. And I think we're
good. I think that'll already be kind of
interesting. Let's go ahead and start
this up. The problem you're going to
find is that it's actually it'll do.
Okay, you can ask it questions like
http880
uh let's see make this jalong
um assistant and it'll be the question
will be uh you know my name is Josh.
Okay, fine. So that'll that should work.
Yeah, great. Okay, so what's my name?
Let's just see if it remembers. Right,
this is what we talked about earlier
with the memory. Uh what's my name?
Right. Uh okay, it's like that movie
momento. So what we have to do is to
give it a way to remember that we're
going to do so with an advisor. Advisor
are how you configure uh you know the
capture of the of the um transcript that
gets propagated on every single
subsequent request. So prompt chat
memory advisor. Okay, we'll say memory
and it'll just be a concurrent hashmap
tig user. Obviously we have
implementations that are backed by
durable storage like SQL or Reddus or
whatever. U so here we're going to say
this.memory.computee compute if absent
user and we're going to say prompt chat
memory advisor and here we're going to
use a message window chat memory uh
passing in a particular implementation
of the repository the in-memory
repository in this case okay so there's
that and when I've configured that uh oh
I'll do this down here when I actually
I'll do this in the uh in the call site
right okay put that there and we'll say
var memory or var
advisor okay so we're going to compute
it if it doesn't already exist if it
then great and that's going to be the
path variable string user coming in from
the URL template there. Okay. And we're
going to pass that that advisor along uh
on the call site. So here we go. Dot
advisor use uh advisor and voila. So
let's let's go ahead and uh uh start
that up and see what that's bought us if
anything right should be certainly a
little bit better situated to answer
this question. My name is Josh. Okay.
What's my name? Okay, great. So, it's
got the memory, but now it doesn't know
about the data and it doesn't know what
it's doing. So, let's rectify both of
those. We can get it to pretend it's
it's an employee for our fictitious dog
adoption agency by giving it a system
prompt. So, let's do that. I happen to
have a system prompt here. Let me just
cat it to the buffer. And wait, that's
wrong. You know what? That's wrong. Dog
it. There we go. Much better. Going to
copy and paste that. Put it here. And
we'll say dot system prompt system.
Okay. There we are. There's this. And uh
that's that's the uh system prompt.
It'll now act as though it's a an
employee of our fictitious dog adoption
agency named Pooch Palace with locations
in Antworp, Soul, Tokyo, Tokyo,
Singapore, Paris, whatever. Okay, let's
now then put that um data, you know, we
want to give it access to the data. The
data is in our database. Uh we're going
to use Spring Data JDBC to get the data
from our SQL database and write it out
to the implementation of the vector
store, which in this case happens to be
the same SQL database, but it not it
doesn't always necessarily need to be
that, right? It could be uh you know
wev8 or chromadb or elastic search or
whatever right so interface dog
repository and indeed there's a
implementation of the vector store
implementation or rather interface for
all those different implementations
right uh I'll tell spring data gdbc to
map that there you go that's the primary
key and let's write that code we're
going to read from the dog repository
and we're going to write out to the
vector store here vector store so I'll
say repository findall for each dog var
and you know we're going to write out a
Spring AI document uh for each record in
the database. So ID name and then
description and then we'll do a
formatted dog ID name description.
Fantastic. Now uh that's a document for
dogs. So obviously obviously uh it's a
it's a uh document. Okay, there we go.
So now we're going to write this out.
We'll say vector store. Oh no. Okay, I'm
learning Vim motions. If you uh see me
struggling here, list of document. All
right, good. So now the finally I want
to tell the model that hey should you
get a request for which uh you know uh
that necessitates necessitates the need
for data go ahead and get it from the uh
vector store we'll configure yet another
advisor a question answer advisor
passing in a pointer to the vector
store. So let's see where that's bought
us if anything. Yeah. So we go over here
http 8080 uh jong um assistant. Well,
here let me just uh we'll do
http controlr controlr again. Control-r
no nothing. Builder. Okay, whatever. So,
http 8080
jong assistant question equals uh do you
have any neurotic dogs? Right, that
should be the question. We're going to
look for our dog Prancer. Okay, yes, we
do have a neurotic dog available for
adoption. Meet Prancer, a demonic
neurotic dog who unfortunately has a
dislike for men, animals, and children.
If you're interested in learning more
about Prancer or arranging a visit,
please let me know. Boy, am I. Who
wouldn't be? I mean, that sounds like
the greatest dog, right? A spicy but
very, very cool doggo. So, what I want
to do is uh avoid reinitializing that.
Obviously, I don't want to do that more
than necessary because these uh calls to
your embedding models, they can be quite
expensive if not in dollars and cents
than in terms of complexity. And by the
way, we have the spring boot actuator on
the class path which gives you
observability which allows you to see
things like how many tokens have been
consumed. That is to say, how much data
you've sent to and fro. Okay, so let's
create a tool that allows this AI model
to help participate in the scheduling of
uh of adoption visits, right? And I'll
just create a simple method here,
schedule. It'll take in the dog ID and
the string dog name. And uh we're going
to return just a a date in the future
just to guarantee that we uh have
something you know that we know was not
hallucinated, right? And we'll give it a
two string. And I'll say system out
scheduling uh the dog ID. Okay. And then
dog name. Uh and then uh we're going to
say at tool description schedule and
appointment
uh point. You can use AI to grammar
correct this to pick up and uh or or
adopt a dog from a pooch palace
location, right? And uh you give it tool
params. And again, remember your parents
always taught you to use your words.
Well, this is what they meant, right?
Use the words um to better to be very
very descriptive in defining the schema
in effect of this tool. Okay, the idea
of the dog. Okay, fine. So there's
there's that. I'm going to now give my
model access to that tool by again just
injecting it into the constructor here
and uh doing that. Okay, souler and
gonna go down here. I'll say default
tools. Okay, scheduler. Let's go ahead
and start that
up. Okay, take this again. So, do you
have any
dogs? Okay, great. We got Prancer now.
Uh that sounds great. Let's pick up that
dog from the uh
fantastic uh when can I schedule an
appointment an appointment to pick up
Prancer from the London
location.
Okay, if if everything's gone to plan,
it says May 16th. Today's the 13th of
May. Fantastic. You can see it's been
there. Now, this is all well and good,
but I'm running on my local machine.
This is a Java tool that I've made
available to my model. it's knowing to
interact with it by the descriptive text
that we've given it. But that said, I
want to be able to repurpose this
business logic from other languages.
Enthropic back way back in November of
2024. Does anybody here remember that
far back? I certainly don't. It's been a
blur. Uh they introduced this new
protocol called MCP. And MCP is model
context protocol. So we're going to spin
up a MCP service here. Uh just open that
up. And remember the Spring AI team
donated the core Java abstraction that
is now the official SDK for MCP. Indeed,
the easiest way to build MCP services on
the JDK is to use Spring AI since we
built the core abstraction and the uh
corresponding integration in Spring AI
itself. So, we're going to export. Now,
we I copied and pasted that code. Don't
ever don't ever do that, okay? Not even
when you're all by yourself at home and
no one is looking. Uh but I'm going to
copy and paste and I'm going to inject
the dog adoption and I'll
say and uh I'll tell this thing to run
on a separate port. I'll say port 8081.
Here we go. And now I've got a dog
adoption scheduleuler sized hole in my
original code. So I need to like uh I
need to replace that with instead a
reference to the MCP remote uh server.
Okay. So let's create a bean here. MCP
sync client. MCP sync client return MCP
sync client uh sorry MCP
client dot from and then it'll be HTTP.
builder and I'll say
localhost
8081 and it'll be
build. Okay. And then technically
technically var mcp is this and I say
return mcp and I think you're supposed
to call mcp.initialize. I always forget.
I'm not really good at the uh the old
software thing, right? Okay. So uh let's
put that here and get rid of that. Okay,
goodbye. Injecting that now instead. And
we're going to replace this with a call
back. Yeah. So, call back new and then
we'll say
um new sync. Okay. Uh MCP sync client
restart. Okay. So, if everything's gone
to plan, we've got over here um oh, you
know what I forgot to do? I'm going to
use the snapshots here as well on my
uhuler. This will go well, I'm sure.
Okay, here we
go. Good. Hello. Okay, good. Snapshot.
Command shift I
reload. Depend that. Okay, so it's
reloading that with the new class path.
Josh, just to let you know, you have uh
one last minute to save all the dogs. No
problem. Here we go. Ready. Uh, do you
have any like
dogs? Yep, we got Prancer. When can I
schedule an appointment to pick up
Prancer from the London
location? And May 16th. So, there's the
original assistant talking via this MCP
protocol over here to theuler module.
Now, my friends, in that brief time,
we've looked at uh just a few of the
things you can do with the new Spring AA
1.0. Again, coming out in just about a
week's time, GA uh you can go to
start.spring.io, get the bits. Um
obviously, the next natural step after
this is to then, you know, you've got
the primitives. You can do oneshot
requests with ease and applied
naturally, it's a very easy thing to
then put that in a sort of a flow, a
structure that allows you to drive
towards a more complex outcome. That's
called agentic programming and this is a
natural thing to do with Spring AI as
well. I want to thank you for your time
and take any and all questions. Thanks
very much.